how like we talked about that practice
but then when it comes to that to a
practical side of it
it's sort of kept in an arm's length
because side of it B what would you mean
like most of the time when practice is
talked about is just sort of talked
about and so entertain as a thought but
I'm on a day to day to day so leaving of
them then it's sort of like so easy to
revert to keeping things in an arm's
length yeah well that's it it's like the hey
that's the well needs to be recognized
even even before you become a mother
like that
the Dhamma in order to be done properly
requires a great deal of giving up yes
theoretically a layperson can practice
the Dharma but from the Dhamma point of
view lay life it's already compromised
it's not a compromise for somebody who
is unaware of the Dhamma and unaware of
the requirements and unaware of what the
practice is but for somebody who is
aware of it
who got kind of got the idea and then
chooses to stay a layman that's a
compromise and that's exactly already
the beginning of keeping the Dharma in
the arm's length so you know where the
Dharma should apply but for whatever
reasons personal you refuse to go in
that direction so you choose to focus
down on the suitors and the instances
where the Buddha sort of did
successfully and
we'll derive you in laypeople and then
oh so I don't have to be a month I don't
have to give up my existence I had to
give up familiarity of my environment I
have to give up my family and I can get
the Dumber well those people were far
far less in number back in the Buddha's
day but laypeople who became such funds
mostly it was monks nuns and there is no
instance of a layperson being in Iran
because it's impossible to live that
life with the fully enlightened
environment the values the whole thing
it's impossible so it always boils down
to those kind of your actions and your
choices and lack of transparency in
regard to it so it's obvious not
everybody can be a monk but everybody is
perfectly capable of not avoiding a
responsibility for that
yeah the lack of transparency
no nothing that's mostly didn't like so
even when you do commit it's after a
while it's very easy to feel fully
justified - oh yeah because becoming a
monk is a necessary step towards
creating the circumstances for the
practice but it's not doesn't mean
automatically you're practicing by
becoming a month and yeah that's another
thing sometimes people need to realize
they think all over for me I'll become a
month that's it that's all I need to do
then I'll be fine
you're still a layman basically even if
you're a monk unless you become suitable
that's the only difference between a
layman and like a member of the Sangha
so you wearing brown cloth wrapped
around you it's just a new fashion
statement until you get the right view
it's it's a statement it's look I'm this
this is my set of values so it's a
necessary statement more often than not
but it doesn't mean you you arrive at
clarity of transparency and so on so you
need to always keep the reasons for
becoming a monk in the first place keep
it in your mind what why do you want to
come up because you want to be free from
suffering so have you free from
suffering simply by becoming a month no
okay so now you can you can actually
practice further and it's when people
forget that that's when you know you're
becoming a monk becomes more like a
career social socially oriented purposes
and so on which is all nice in the world
in manner but it's it's a layman's
undertaking
if you know somebody that doesn't want
to practice amateurs it's a lemon that's
actually fun you can
well you can't complain about them but
that's a different topic but it's the
problem is when when you know the value
of the Dharma you know what it entails
at least an extent but then you choose
to justify not doing it because you know
you need to be a layman
so that's why it's a compromise that's
where you kind of disqualify yourself
from proper understanding of the Dharma
would you say like um keep an eye out
for your anxieties yes keep an eye for
the suffering because all of these acts
of covering things up from yourself it's
to cover up the responsibility because
it's felt unpleasantly if by some
miracle responsibility would be felt
pleasantly nobody would be covering it
and everybody would automatically go to
a tournament you towards full
enlightenment but it's the opposite
responsibility is not pleasant never is
there was no will be and there was never
a problem the problem is you not being
able to endure that discomfort and
habitually looking away from it giving
in to distracting yourself from it and
the more you do it the more dependent
you become on doing it doing that
avoidance sort of in like um like crap
using anxiety as a criteria
yes I said using anxiety secretaries and
other way of saying using discerning the
liability to suffering is a criteria
because it doesn't matter if you're a
layman doesn't matter if you're a monk
what matters is are you still liable to
suffering and it's it's
virtually inseparable liable to
suffering it's virtually inseparable
inseparable from being Elena so yeah by
proxy then if you really want to commit
to free yourself from suffering you have
to recognize you need to commit to
change in your environment you cannot
live in the world around that it's fully
based upon values of sensuality family
accompanying distraction desires lack of
restraint and somehow go beyond that but
yes you can say oh it's not it's not my
fault then I'm not a monk I can be monk
or you can say it's all my fault that I
have to be a layman but it is your fault
they used to lie about suffering so
doesn't matter what you are your fault
is whether you're liable suffering or
not why because suffering is nothing to do
why because suffering is nothing to do
with any external circumstance
whatsoever if you suffer it's because
there is craving in your mind not in the
things that made you made you suffer
similarly and that's something you're
always responsible for but if as a rule
of thumb you avoid responsibility for
even things that are not so deeply
rooted you're not gonna see this that's really
you're not gonna see this that's really
you start accepting responsibility for
everything else in order to in order to
be able to see it in this level so being
a monk is basically you should suffer
better and you are own better focus yes
not not by default you still need to
exercise certain you know reasoned
decisions because you know some of the
monasteries are simply not suitable some
of the places are not suitable so not
being a monk in any tradition is not
suitable you can be a monk and people
who think it's the same Buddhist monk in
the tradition it doesn't keep winner it
simply doesn't have the precepts or has
completely different presets that are
not on the same level so you need to be
you know I'm not saying I only to be in
the right tradition but you need to be
in the right set of values
which means you need to know the set of
values and you need the suitors and you
get the set of values because yes you
will have like terawatt amongst which is
what we are many of them would not keep
this the rules that you're supposed to
keep and you just have things eyes it's
not your problem
so doesn't mean like a whole stare of
heart didn't know people individually
choose to not worth here not adhere to
rules or or things that they know should
be adhere to so you can still choose to
go to that duration or somewhat other
tradition that doesn't necessarily keep
those rules but then you can keep those
rules if you can but if you think that
the environment will prevent you from
keeping rules because of you know what
people would expect from you and so on
then you shouldn't be going into that
environment so it's a meaner ordaining
in a tear of other tradition but in some
temple monastery that it's all about
like you know money and events and so on
well that's not something you'd you
would want to do if you want to practice
Dhamma
so precepts are a a personal choice a
personal commitment yes yeah of course
yeah it's again comes through through
that recognition of personal
responsibility there's no commandment that demands from
there's no commandment that demands from
you to do it but if you want to practice
the Dharma they are necessary basis for
it so it's not optional that's why it's
see it would be more honest if you say I
don't want to practice Dharma and I'll
go ahead and sort of not keep the
precepts then saying I am practicing the
Dharma and I don't need to keep the
precepts which is what you hear people
relatively often say no no you don't
need to give up your life you don't need
to give up sensuality and you can be
enlightened well not according to the
Buddha which ironically you profess to
follow
so yes today many things vastly
different things are called Buddhism but
it doesn't mean that the Buddhist
teaching all of that and if you want the
Sahaba know what the Buddha was teaching
well you can't know 100% because he's
long gone but you can certainly know
what is least likely to be wrong in
terms of the teachings so you can know
what is most likely closest to what he's
been teaching what all the traditions
agree with the earliest texts and that's
how okay so this is my starting point
it's important all be perfect cuz it's
been two and a half million years since
but this is my starting point so I'll
start investigating this but not like I
pick and choose that which will suit my
already predetermined lifestyle that I
do not want to change
why because I'm too afraid and you know
that you're covering something up if you
get emotionally disturbed on account of
encountering the opposing view if
somebody says you should eat your duty
to give up delaila and if you feel
affected by that Oh get angry with
person who said it on top of that you're
covering things up not because you're a
layman because you're not a monk it's
because you're avoiding responsibility
for what you are it's hard not to which
is why you are in that environment in
that setup and I think the truth is
before as a layperson myself when I
started doing the suitors that
fortunately became very clear to me the
Buddha outline says the only thing that
matters in the world is suffering is
freedom from it whatever you do is an
account of how you feel I need to
prolong pleasure because not enough
pleasure is suffering or to avoid pain
because enduring pain is suffering and
he says and this is the way out come and
see for yourself literally
and I remember reading it and he was
obvious oh I do need to become I don't
need to give up the world because see
you know tell me suffering there is the
way about there's the way out you can
follow it but you don't have to it's not
literally that I will be like enduring
the eternal damnation
if I don't become a monk but then at the
same time I felt oh so now I'm
responsible who better I go forward and
become a monk and pursue this freedom
from suffering to the good of teachers
and I'm equally responsible for not
doing that so if I choose to stay a
layman I cannot complain for whatever
happens to me for the rest of my life
and future whatever whatever your
beliefs were so in other words you might
not be responsible for particular things
good or bad that happened to you but
you're responsible for choosing to stay
in the environment where these things
can happen environment being some sorry
fundamentally and I thought oh that's
it's quite an obvious choice and
obviously for me it was a no-brainer
choice because really like the only the
only way you could stay in the
environment that makes you liable
pressured by feeling good or bad doesn't
matter is to ignore that then you are then
is to ignore that then you are then
inaudible which I couldn't ignore
because the choice became very clear so
then becoming a monk felt like nope like
some mystical duty did I need to do to
be saved you just felt like oh it's just
a step towards this right direction of
freedom from suffering just a step
towards the environment that can provide
me with better conditions for practice
more efficient practice because most of
the lay life even if the one if you want
to practice the Dharma but most of your
energy would be spent just sort of
fending off sensuality and your will and
company crowd and bombardment and it's
no there's no way you would on top of
that then will make all the amount of
necessary amount of effort to actually
discern through that
mark and swamp of ignorance but yes you
don't spend most of time just fending
off things then here you will have
enough effort built up to start looking
through things and and deal with it yes
when people don't want to leave that
sexuality yeah see and the only reason
you wouldn't want to leave some
Charlotte is because you still avoid
responsibility for it you don't have to
leave it but what you have to do is stop
ignoring the fact that you are
responsible for staying there when
people say yeah oh you're so lucky you
can be among um oh we are lucky in as
much we're still alive
haven't been like a riddled with
sickness and song yeah there is luck
that's often pure chance a bit maybe
we'll be careful make sure you kind of
you know use your body don't get
indignant and whatever else but overall
that's as far as the luck goes
everything else is based on the choices
Mark's individually made I did not wake
up one morning and suddenly became a
fully ordained mind no you have to leave
the home you have to leave the family
the the you know the people you revolve
you head to which means it can never be
pleasant ever but you recognize
responsibility you recognize the value
of it it is when you know that then you
just try to keep it as you said at the
arms line so you are luckier mark and
I'm unlucky
either way none of us is responsible for
our own situation where people say I
can't be a man you know because I have
the family to look after
yeah that is true that is a reason you
can't be a man but why do you have a
family be sure to look after we're just
sort of magically thrown upon you you
just woke up one morning with six
children you have to look after know you
each time individually chose that to
engage in a full-on centralized the
resulting children sometimes planned or
unplanned doesn't matter
they cannot happen accidentally
so now you have to look after the
consequences of your actions yes that's
exactly what samsara is but that's what
I mean it's not a conservative what you
do is stop big nodding responsibility
for that and then you know whether you
really want to be a monk or you you're
fine by staying Elena you never be clear
on that for as long as you know
responsibility for the situation you're
already in and say someone wants to go
or even to get a taste of while staying
a layman what what what he should he or
she should do can you know precepts like
what precepts entail before you commit
to them can you like up this is tea
whistles I'll have no no no you can know
them in terms of you can know what they
are and what they require you to abstain
from and practice and be mindful of but
until you start doing it situates like
asking can you feel the heat of the fire
that you would have lit up with these
wet sticks if they were dry no you can
know that there would be a heat as a
result of the fire but you can't feel
that heat for as long as you don't dry
the sticks so as long as you don't dry
on your behavior of greed aversion
delusion conceit and everything else you
can't feel the heat of the Dhamma in
terms of that wisdom and that liberation
from suffering so you need to commit to
it yes you need to keep the precepts you
know the free mind to start drying out
and then the wisdom can take place
you cannot foresee what's you can see
see in the epsilon the abstract level
yes the heat will probably be the result
but what did he do how it felt and how
its experience you don't know because
your sticks were always way
so that's I mean you might choose then
that whatever your family you commit
your job is more important to you or
rather having the insecurity from giving
these things up is something you don't
want and on account of it you say well
this time is all good but you know I
like being being a layman that's
absolutely fine as long as you don't use
that to the same time cover up
responsibility for that very choice
that's all because if you don't cover up
the responsibility for their very choice
now you will feel responsible for not
following the way out of suffering for
staying in the environment that provides
you with pleasure you are familiar with
and provides you also possibilities of
suffering that you have to deal with and
then endure that responsibility of that
choice and that's actually where the
good was teaching to lay people didn't
say you should become monks and nuns he
said you should all be aware that you
are the owners of your actions the
burden of your choice is always on you
so choose wisely choose skillfully still
even as a layman choose according to the
fact research as in not out of greed
aversion delusion don't harm others all
these things because it's the same
principle so the balls things basically
signaling the responsibility that's what
ignorant comes first it's the root of
everything you said like familiarity
yeah and earlier that similar you gave
like you always had breadsticks yeah you
don't know anything else yes when you
have a degree of faith initially to
recognize extra clay that yeah sticks
try out its moves greater likelihood
that I'll light the fire so now I just
have to endure for as long as it takes
for them to dry out and maybe huh don't
jump back into the water because there
was my familiar environment and then it
will stop being your familiar
environment and the sensory strengths
will become your familiar environment
and then it will require you effort not
to restrain but to go back to sensuality
and that's how you know you're on the
right path
so um the reason like giving things out
keeping precepts accepting
responsibility is unpleasant is could
you keep avoiding it you always have
been avoiding it
so someone hears this starts with their
sense restraint hmm what next
how do you I was settled by the the lay
person or even a month a month yeah so
you start with a sense restraint as a
necessary basis for understanding the
Dhamma so the next step is then to start
contemplating things so why do you want
to understand the dumb doing separate to
not suffer to not suffer so now on the
basis of sensory strength so you haven't
been engaging with sensuality and been
giving into your will expression of it
where is your suffering
well say you don't know like all your
life all you knew was sexuality
okay I think we let this for example say
you want something you have a central
desire and you restrain yourself you're
not doing it it's felt unpleasantly what
is unpleasant feeling the feeling of
displeasure why is it a pleasure
this well it's pressuring its itself
alright so there is pressure left and
right but why is this pressure felt
unpleasantly by you
says this is it because of the because
you said no to yourself you would want
to jump at that sort of conclusion but
not really no oh you can say yes it is
it's because you said no to yourself
that's the most obvious answer yeah
but why did you say no to yourself was
there nothing and then suddenly you just
said no to yourself and pain a reason as
the direct result of saying no to
yourself what was there something before
you said no to self to which you said no
so then your pain started before you
said no the you saying no was not the
first point of that whole experience
because see when you like if say no is
where the pain is means or anytime you
say no it would be felt painfully but
that's another case if I offer you this
poisonous drink to drink it they will
cause you pain for weeks and you say no
to it would you suffer on account of
that or would you be elated and happy on
account of that very no you be elated
and happy because the basis for saying
no is what determines whether it's felt
pleasantly or not pleasantly so now when
you say no to your sensual desire and
you suffer on account of it that pain is
in central desire and saying no reveals
the pain that started with sensual
desire if sensual desire were truly
Pleasant as I said that many times
before you wouldn't feel pressured
towards it but why do you need sensual
desire were Pleasant you wouldn't need
to act out of it because desire in
itself would be bliss but it's not isn't
it sensual desire means you need to act
and get and obtain and maintain and
protect and engage with it more and so
on which means it touches you painfully
and you want to get rid of the pain so
that's always the first and always there
the the main framework for an engagement
with sensuality doesn't matter the
pleasure you can get secondary
from it it's always rooted first in
trying to avoid the pain of it so sense
restraint can never be the reason for
neither pain nor pleasure abstaining
from action cannot be the reason for
pain no pleasure
it can only reveal the reason for pain
or pleasure that's already implied in
the action you're restraining from so as
you're already committing to saying no
not seeing you say no to things yeah so
initially you're gonna blame your sense
restraint for your pain but as I said if
there was ever truly the case means
since I mean saying no to your senses
would always be unpleasant but it isn't
saying no to the harmful exposure of the
senses is for Pleasant it's felt Oh God
don't you pull it there but it's the
same act of same saying no - I refuse
this site I refuse this taste so then
when you feel the pain of sense
restraint stop missing then - finding it
and you can only stop missing dent if
eyeing it if you started practicing
sense restraint first so that's what you
should do once you start practicing
sense restraint start seeing that the
pain is not in that the pain is that
which you're restraining yourself from
so how long do you hurt you there is no
prescription as the Buddha said himself
sometimes half a night is enough
sometimes you may need a full day seven
days seven months seven years but the
point is if you do need - the results
will have to come you cannot be doing it
rightly without the right results
results - the finger from suffering that
is inconceivable so that's another thing
you should factor in yeah you need to be
patient to some extent but then at the
same time don't pretend don't think like
oh so there's ever never any verifiable
result for me I just need to do this out
of faith and there is nothing to be
attained anyway no there is there's a
lot to be attained and if you're not
attaining it is because you're not doing
things rightly as simple as that and if
you don't believe me well read the
suitors many occasions that would have
said in many different ways but always
the best stimuli was that the hand
sitting on her eggs so even if the hen
wishes may I be a lightened or may my
chicks pierce out safely into this world from
pierce out safely into this world from
these shells they want because she's not
sitting on the eggs so even if the monk
wishes may reach enlightenment he won't
because he's not doing the right
practice now the other hand she sits on
the right and even if she doesn't wish
may my chick spear saw the she'll safely
and come into this world they will cause
she's sitting yes so if the similarly if
the monk is doing the practice correctly
even if he doesn't wish may my mind be
purified from greedy delusion may I stop
being liable to suffering he will
because she's doing it the right way so
when you hear people saying is nothing
to be attained it's because they haven't
attained anything and they're covering
it up if there is nothing to be obtained
why does every virtually every suit that
talks about the tenants let's see having
desire for attainments is unpleasant and
people don't want displeasure on account
of the Dhamma practice they want soft
inspirational poetic words they will
make them feel good not feel bad so
that's literally like you go to the
doctor and you ask for the curing says
here it's a bitter it's gonna make you
vomit have diarrhea what you bet torture
you but it will cure you and then you'll
be fine oh yeah but I don't know the
side effects so then you continue
pretending you know leo
so I think that's where he started isn't
it like hmm being likely the arm's
length ya know it's something like you
can you you won't even see the value of
being practical and clear and
understanding in the meaning for as long
as you're avoiding your own personal
responsibility that's you need to stop
avoiding responsibility for what you
choose to to be to do to attend and then
you get you get a better picture then
you will be unable to ignore as much
and as I said yeah wanting to be free
from suffering is yet another desire but
as the Buddha said it's the desire that
can then start directing you towards
finding about the demise which will then
eventually result in freedom from desire
so it's a desire they will eventually
cancel all the other desire including
itself so that's what it would have
meant when he said desire is to be
abandoned by the means of desiring
cravings to be abandoned means of
craving you crave for liberation from
suffering in craving in suffering but
because of craving for liberation not
craving for some charity and everything
else you actually get to make the effort
discern layer by layer one liberation is
and by doing so you free yourself from
the very craving they made you do it
so it's a good craving and bad credit
good craving will cancel itself bad
people will perpetuate itself you won't
see either if you if you keep avoiding
and turning a blind eye to the
responsibility of your actions in your
situation and your choices in all the
results that come your way as a result
of where you chose to be that's what the
Buddha compared the whole situation of
staying in samsara like being in the
house that roofs on fire and it's
collapsing bit by bit and it will crush
you any compelling enlightenment -
leaving that environment
he didn't compare enlightenment to
repairing the roof beams or reroofing
the tiles which is usually what people
want dammit - do I want to fix my life
so nothing bothers me but also I can
still stay in the house no Dhamma takes
you out of your life out of existence
overcomes it as in you leave the house
that isn't fire not you repair it
extinguish the fire you leave the
dangerous environment or choose not to
then you can't complain when you get
burnt a little bit bit more and then
eventually when the whole roof car
starts coming down
most times I can you do the dum-dum much
so you can get back to what what do you
yes I do the Dhamma as a way of such
kind of psychological psychotherapy
dealing with things that currently
bother me but only so that can return to
things that don't bother me then to see
that whether they're things bothering
you are not bothering you either way
you're affected by things and that's
where the problem is